Tufts Student Activism Collection MS270
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Student Activism Collection
2015 -- 2020
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS270
.25 Linear Feet
7 Digital Object(s) Of the 7 digital objects, 1 digital object comprises 13 files.
150.7 Megabytes
3 Web sites
This collection consists of materials documenting Tufts student activism on topics including climate change, sex crimes, Antisemitism, and labor organizing.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by topic or provenance.
Biographical / Historical
Tufts University was founded as a Universalist institution of higher education in 1852, beginning a long history of student activism. Universalism in the United States has historically had a politically liberal or progressive bent. In the 19th century, Universalists advocated for abolition, the separation of church and state, and the ordination of women.
Evidence of student activism at Tufts can be traced back to the early 20th century and Jackson College for Women. Jackson College was Tufts University's coordinate college, which was an alternative to coeducational or women's colleges. Women at Jackson College engaged in activist organizing as early as that school's founding in 1910. During World War I, Jackson College students contributed to the Tufts War Garden. These gardens, also known as "victory gardens," were planted at private residences and public parks and were meant to supplement food rations during wartime and boost morale. Jackson College students also advocated for women's suffrage prior to the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution, which granted some women the right to vote in 1920. Some Jackson students also fought for Nicola Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti's release from prison in the 1920s. This highly publicized and controversial case led to the conviction and execution of the two men amidst intense anti-immigrant, anti-Italian, and anti-anarchist sentiments.
One of the most intense periods of activism at Tufts was from the late 1960s through the early 1970s, reflecting the civil rights, anti-war, women's, gay rights, and environmental movements across the nation. Tufts s tudents protested the Vietnam War, U.S. involvement in apartheid South Africa, for increased representation of and support for African Americans on campus, and for greater student involvement in the Tufts administration. Opposition to the Vietnam War prompted student protests against military recruitment and against the presence of the ROTC on campus.
The decades of student activism that began in the 1960s are in large part responsible for the creation of the identity centers—the "Group of Six"—that are now part of the Division of Student Diversity and Inclusion. Advocacy and protests related to the experience of students of African descent at a predominantly white institution led to the creation of the Africana Center in 1969. In 1972, the Women's Center was founded as a student-run and Tufts Community Union Senate funded organization. That same year, the Tufts Gay Community (TGC) organization was formed, which eventually became the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Center. Following an incident in which a campus fraternity had their pledges yell racial slurs outside the Asian-American House, the Start House, in 1982, the Asian-American Center was founded in 1983. The Latino Center, now the Latinx Center, was founded in 1993, amid calls to establish a center comparable to those that supported African-American and Asian-American students. The FIRST Resource Center, which supports first-generation, low-income, and undocumented students, was founded in 2018, building on initiatives led by first-generation students.
From the 1980s to the present, student activism has continued, focusing on issues including diversity and racial justice, climate change and fossil fuel divestment, labor issues, tuition increases, sexual misconduct and assault, policing and police violence, and protests against the Gulf and Iraq Wars. Students have protested the impact of these issues both on the Tufts campus and beyond. Protests have taken varied forms, including rallies, marches, sit-ins, hunger strikes, die-ins, strikes, and petitions. Many activist student organizations have formed and dissolved over the years, including both university-recognized and funded organizations and organizations that are unofficial or unrecognized by the University.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collected by Digital Collections and Archives staff, 2019 -- 2020, accessions MS-2021-005 and MS-2021-007.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials documenting Tufts student activism, including fliers, stickers, and photographs, on topics including climate activism, sex crimes, and Antisemitism. Additionally, it contains web crawls completed by DCA staff to capture the web presence for activist groups on campus.
Related Materials
MS194, Students Against Transphobia Records
MS259, Tufts Dining Action Coalition Records
MS264, Tufts Food Rescue Collaborative Records
UA024, Activities and Organizations Records
UA218, Tufts Collective for Men Against Violence Records
UA249, Metcalf Hall Protest Posters and Resident Life Records
Social justice; Student activism
- Climate activism records, 2019; MS270.000001; .10 Linear Feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains fliers, stickers, and photographs from the Tufts Climate Strike in 2019.
  - Climate strike fliers and stickers, 2019 September -- 2019 December; MS270.000002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Climate Strike photographs, 2019 September 20; MS270.000003; 111 Megabytes; 1 Digital Object(s) One digital obejct comprising 13 files
    Open for research.
- Tufts Cannon photographs, 2018 October -- November; MS270.000004; 39.7 Megabytes; 6 Digital Object(s)
  Photographs of the Tufts Cannon, located on the Medford, Massachusetts campus, which is frequently repainted throughout the academic year.
  - Tufts Cannon painted to read 'We Believe Dr. Ford' (view from the right), 2018 October 03; MS270.000008; 6.2 Megabytes
    Cannon painted "We Believe Dr. Ford," taken a week after Christine Blasey Ford testified against Supreme Court nominee Brett Kavanaugh in front of the United States Senate.
  - Tufts Cannon painted to read 'We Believe Dr. Ford' (view from the right), 2018 October 03; MS270.000009; 6.1 Megabytes
  - Tufts Cannon painted to read 'We Believe Survivors' (view from the left), 2018 October 03; MS270.000010; 6.6 Megabytes
    Cannon painted "We Believe Survivors," taken a week after Christine Blasey Ford testified against Supreme Court nominee Brett Kavanaugh in front of the United States Senate.
  - Tufts Cannon painted to read 'Stronger than Hate' (view from the left), 2018 November 03; MS270.000005; 6.6 Megabytes
    Cannon painted "Stronger than Hate" and bearing an image of the Tree of Life, Stars of David, and a list of the victims of the mass shooting at the Tree of Life synagogue in Pittsburgh, PA, on October 27, 2018.
  - Tufts Cannon painted in response to mass shooting at the Tree of Life synagogue (view from the right), 2018 November 03; MS270.000006; 7.1 Megabytes
  - Tufts Cannon painted in response to mass shooting at the Tree of Life synagogue (view from the right), 2018 November 03; MS270.000007; 7.1 Megabytes
- Web crawls, 2015 -- 2020; MS270.000011; 3 Web sites
  This series is arranged chronologically by the date of each website's first capture.
  This series contains websites identified by DCA staff that document student activism on the Tufts Campus. It includes websites and social media sites for groups organized for fair labor conditions on campus.
  Other Finding Aids
  The Tufts Dining Coalition and Tufts Labor Coalition web presence is being captured as part of the Student Organizations collection in Archive-It. Please visit https://archive-it.org/collections/6387 for the complete collection.
  Additional websites documenting student activism are being captured as part of the Tufts Student Activism collection. Please visit https://archive-it.org/collections/14863 for the complete collection.
  - Tufts Labor Coalition - Jumbo Janitors Facebook, 2015 -- 2016; MS270.000012; 1 Web sites
    General
    Crawled quarterly (inactive).
  - Tufts Labor Coalition - Home | Facebook, 2018 -- 2020; MS270.000013; Tufts Labor Coalition; 1 Web sites
    Frequency: quarterly crawl.
  - Tufts Labor Coalition - Twitter, 2020 December 16; MS270.000015; Tufts Labor Coalition; 1 Web sites
  - Tufts Dining Action Coalition - Home | Facebook, 2018 -- 2020; MS270.000014; Tufts Dining Action Coalition; 1 Web sites